Finding Aid for Law School (University of Michigan) Photograph and Artwork Collection, 1870-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Law School (University of Michigan) Photograph and Artwork Collection 1870-1994 1900-1950
University of Michigan--Law School.
2009057 Bimu 2
Portraits, photographs, and artwork previously displayed in the University of Michigan Law School, featuring prominent alumni, faculty, notable figures in the legal profession, and images of the Law School grounds. Also, records concerning art owned by the Law School, including surveys, inventories, reports, and scattered information on specific portraits.
1.0 linear feet in 4 boxes
3 items
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The material was received from the Law School in 2008 (Donor no. 343 ).
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
For many years, the University of Michigan Law School solicited portraits of its most prominent graduates to decorate its classrooms, study areas, and public spaces with law-related themes. Through these efforts many new portraits were added to the large body of paintings and photographic portraits already displayed in the Law School. Although the Law School made several partial inventories, no comprehensive effort was made to inventory all the Law School artwork until the university received support from the Michigan Commission on Art in Public Places in 1988, at which point a detailed description of all the art was made.
In 1994, the Law School put together an updated catalog of its art, and in 1997-98, additional inventories were made for risk management and insurance purposes, but they lacked the level of detail of the 1988 inventory. In 1993-94, several administrators proposed that much of the art be removed from the Law School. The works were re-evaluated based on their condition and subject matter, and eventually most were removed from classrooms and study areas.
The framed photographs, documents, and artwork that were removed from the Law School were stored in various locations throughout the Law School. In 2008, the removed artwork was transferred to the Bentley Historical Library. For storage and preservation purposes, most images were removed from their frames with the exception of oil paintings.
The University of Michigan Law School Photograph and Artwork Collection contains portraits of faculty, alumni, and notable legal figures as well as several inventories of the art, and documentation requesting portraits, risk management measures, and decisions to remove much of the artwork.
The records are arranged into four series: Documentation, Individual Photographs and Portraits, Other Artwork and Documents, and Oil Paintings.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Law Quadrangle (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan. Law School--Alumni.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Documentation
  The series Documentation includes files on the Art and Memorials Committee plans and reports, 1976-1978; information on specific portraits (which is not comprehensive); various inventories of the artwork and risk management documents; correspondence concerning requests for portraits, 1975-1977; and decisions to remove the portraits from display.
  - Art and Memorials Committee Plan and Report 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Art Inventories by University of Michigan Law School (Box 1)
  - Commission on Art in Public Places Surveys 1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Requests for Portraits 1975-1977, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Information on Specific Portraits:
    - Thomas Cooley (Box 1)
    - Jason Honigman (Box 1)
    - Wade McCree (Box 1)
    - Frank Murphy (Box 1)
    - Richard Wellman (Box 1)
  - Insurance and Risk Management (Box 1)
  - Law School Art Catalog 1994 (Box 1)
  - Removal of Portraits 1993-1994 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series is comprised of individual photos (both informal photos and formal portraits) of Law School alumni, faculty and legal notables not associate with the university, as well as some composite and group photos of students faculty Many of these items are oversized. The photographs of alumni and faculty may be original photographs or copies; the copied photographs could be enlargements of newspaper clippings or photographs taken of hand drawn portraits. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by the subject's last name. All individual photos are listed in single alphabetical listing, but the oversized items are stored in boxes 2-4.
  All the items in the Photographs series were received from the Law School and were removed from their original frames for storage and preservation purposes.
  - Alumni
    - Abe, Kazuhisa (Box 2)
      (oversized)
    - Adams, Paul L. (Box 1)
    - Aldrich, Edgar (Box 1)
      (also oversized)
    - Ariyoshi, George R. (Box 1)
    - Ashurst, Henry F. (2) (Box 1)
    - Avery, Sewell Lee (Box 1)
    - Babst, Earl D. (Box 1)
    - Barkdull, Howard L. (Box 1)
    - Beadle, William H. H. (Box 1)
    - Beardsley, Charles S. (Box 1)
    - Berry, Mary (Box 1)
    - Black, Charles C. (Box 1)
    - Blatt, George N., Sr. (Box 1)
    - Boardman, John Dixon (Box 1)
    - Booth, Fenton W. (Box 1)
    - Brimmer, Clarence A. (Box 1)
    - Brown, John R. (Box 2)
    - Bulkley, Harry C. (Box 2)
    - Burch, Rousseau A. (Box 2)
    - Butzel, Henry M. (Box 2)
    - Canales, Jose Tomas (Box 1)
    - Cargo, David F. (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, William L. (Box 1)
    - Cartwright, James Henry (Box 1)
    - Chatterton, Fenimore (Box 1)
    - Clark, Chase (Box 1)
    - Cooperrider, Luke K. (Box 2)
    - Crockett, William F. (Box 1)
    - Darrow, Clarence (Box 1)
    - Daugherty, Harry Micajah (Box 1)
    - Dawson, John P. (Box 1)
    - Day, William R. (Box 1)
    - De Vries, Marion (Box 1)
    - Day, William R. (Box 1)
    - De Vries, Marion (Box 1)
    - Denby, Edwin C. (Box 1)
    - Denison, Arthur C. (Box 2)
    - Dethmers, John R. (Box 1)
    - Dickinson, Donald M. (Box 2)
    - Donovan, Dennis (Box 1)
    - Downey, Sheridan (Box 2)
    - Downing, Warwick M. (Box 1)
    - Eager, Henry I. (Box 1)
    - Engel, Albert J. (Box 2)
    - Fauri, Fedele (Box 1)
    - Feikens, John (Box 1)
    - Ferguson, Homer (Box 2)
    - Fiske, Robert B. (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, John W. (Box 1)
    - Freeman, Ralph M. (Box 1)
    - Fukuda, Robert Kiyoshi (Box 1)
    - Garcia-Calderon, Manuel Alfredo (Box 2)
    - Geddes, Donald Frederick (Box 1)
    - Gibson, Ernest W. (Box 2)
    - Gilbert, William B. (Box 2)
    - Good, James W. (Box 2)
    - Grant, Claudius Buchanan (Box 2)
      (2 oversized)
    - Griffin, Robert P. (Box 2)
    - Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Box 2)
    - Gubow, Lawrence (Box 1)
    - Harper, Fowler, V. (Box 2)
    - Hart, Philip A. (Box 2)
    - Harvey, James (Box 1)
    - Herrick, Lott R. (Box 1)
    - Hitchcock, Gilbert M. (Box 2)
    - Horton, Albert Howell (Box 1)
    - Humphrey, George M. (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Henry L. (Box 1)
    - Jones, Harrison (Box 1)
    - Jones, Paul (Box 1)
    - Kashiwa, Shiro (Box 1)
    - Kasuya (Hashimoto), Gisan (Box 1)
    - Katzen, Sally (Box 1)
    - Kearse, Amalya (Box 1)
    - Kelley, Cornelius (Box 1)
    - King, William J. (Box 2)
    - Knappen, Loyal (Box 2)
    - Knox, William W. (Box 1)
    - Levin, Charles L. (Box 1)
    - Lindemer, Lawrence B. (Box 1)
    - MacChesney, Nathan William (Box 1)
    - Mahoney, Charles H. (Box 1)
    - Main, John F. (Box 2)
    - Marland, Ernest W. (Box 1)
    - Martinez, Quintin Amador (Box 1)
    - Maybury, William C. (Box 1)
    - McCumber Porter J. (Box 2)
    - McGugin, Dan Erle (Box 1)
    - McLaughlin, Andrew C. (Box 2)
    - Means, Rice W. (Box 2)
    - Meiklejohn, George D. (Box 1)
    - Metcalf, Henry H. (Box 1)
    - Mizuha, Jack H. (Box 1)
    - Moise, Irwin (Box 1)
    - Moody, Blair, Jr. (Box 1)
    - Moore, Clarence William (Box 1)
    - Moore, Joseph B. (Box 1)
    - Muehl, William A. (Box 1)
    - Mullendore, William C. (Box 1)
    - Murfin, James Orin (Box 2)
    - Murphy, Frank (2 oversized) (Box 1)
    - Murphy, Loren E. (Box 1)
    - Nichols, David A. (Box 1)
    - Norval, Theophilus L. (Box 1)
    - O'Brien, Thomas J. (Box 1)
    - Olson, Culbert L. (Box 1)
    - Parrish, Frank Merrill (Box 1)
    - Parsons, Charles F. (Box 1)
    - Perry, Stuart A. (Box 1)
    - Philip, George (Box 1)
    - Phillips, Orie L. (Box 2)
    - Plumley, Frank (Box 2)
    - Poole, Cecil F. (Box 1)
    - Porter, Robert William (Box 2)
    - Potter, Charles W. (Box 1)
    - Pratt, Philip (Box 1)
    - Quarles, Joseph V. (Box 2)
    - Rendlen, Albert L. (Box 1)
    - Renfrew, Charles B. (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, Frederick (Box 2)
    - Ricks, Jesse Jay (Box 1)
    - Riner, John A. (Box 1)
    - Rogers, Edward Sidney (Box 1)
    - Roth, J. Stephen (Box 1)
    - Rudolph, Herbert B. (Box 1)
    - Sartori, Joseph S. (Box 1)
    - Sharp, William Graves (Box 2)
    - Sharpe, Edward MacGlen (Box 2)
    - Shaw, Elwyn R. (Box 1)
    - Shenk, John W. (Box 1)
    - Shively, Benjamin F. (Box 2)
    - Simons, Charles C. (Box 2)
    - Smith, Talbot (Box 1)
    - Souris, Theodore (Box 1)
    - Storckman, Clem F. (Box 1)
    - Sutherland, George (Box 1)
    - Sycip, Albino Z. (Box 1)
    - Tavares, C. Nils (2) (Box 1)
    - Tennant, John S. (Box 1)
    - Theis, Frank (Box 1)
    - Thomas, Lawson, E. (Box 1)
    - Tietjens, Norman O. (Box 1)
    - Townsend, Charles E. (Box 2)
    - Underwood, Thomas (Box 1)
    - Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick (Box 2)
    - Voelker, John D. (Box 1)
    - Walbridge, Cyrus P. (Box 1)
    - Walden, Austin Thomas (Box 1)
    - Walsh, Charles Clinton (Box 1)
    - Wanty, George P. (Box 1)
    - Warner, William W. (Box 2)
    - Waterman, Charles W. (Box 2)
    - Watrous, Charles L. (Box 1)
    - Weaver, Samuel Pool (Box 1)
    - Weinman, Carl A. (Box 1)
    - Wheeler, Burton K. (Box 1)
    - Whiting, Charles S. (Box 1)
    - Williams, G. Mennen (Box 1)
    - Wolfson, Julian A. (Box 1)
    - Wu, John (Box 2)
  - Faculty
    - Aigler, Ralph W. (Box 3)
    - Allen, Francis A. (Box 3)
    - Angell, James B. (Box 3)
    - Bates, Henry Moore (Box 1)
    - Betts, Helen L. (Registrar) 1956-1980 (Box 3)
    - Bishop, William (Box 3)
    - Blume, Wirt W. (Box 3)
    - Boudeman, Dallas (Box 3)
    - Browder, Olin L., Jr. (Box 3)
    - Campbell, James V. (Box 3)
    - Coffey, Hobart R. (Box 3)
    - Conely, Edwin F. (Box 3)
    - Conrad, Alfred F. (Box 3)
    - Cooley, Thomas M. (Box 1)
    - Dawson, John P. (Box 3)
    - Dewey, Horace W. (Box 1)
    - Durfee, Edgar N. (Box 3)
    - Estep, Samuel D. (Box 3)
    - Ewell, Marshall Davis (Box 1)
    - Griffin, Levi Thomas (Box 1)
    - James, Laylin K. (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Elias F. (Box 1)
    - Joiner, Charles W. (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Frank R. (Box 3)
    - Kent, Charles A. (Box 1)
    - Knowlton, Jerome Cyril (Box 3)
    - Leidy, Paul (Box 1)
    - McCree, Wade H., Jr. (Box 3)
    - Murray, Katherine C. (Registrar) 1920-1956 (Box 1)
    - Niehuss, Marvin L. (Box 3)
    - Oppenheim, S. Chesterfield (Box 3)
    - Palmer, George E. (Box 3)
    - Pierce, William J. (Box 3)
    - Plant, Marcus, L. (Box 3)
    - Polasky, Alan N. (Box 1)
    - Pond, Ashley (Box 1)
    - Proffitt, Roy F. (Box 3)
    - Reed, Frank F. (Box 1)
    - Reed, John W. (Box 3)
    - Rogers, Edward S. (Box 1)
    - Rogers, Henry Wade (Box 1)
      (also two oversized)
    - Sandalow, Terrance (Box 3)
    - Shartel, Burke W. (Box 3)
    - Simes, Lewis M. (Box 3)
    - Smith, Allan F. (Box 3)
    - Smith, Russell A. (Box 3)
    - St. Antoine, Theodore J. (Box 3)
    - Stason, E. Blythe (Box 1)
    - Stein, Eric (Box 3)
    - Tracy, John. E. (Box 1)
    - Vinogradoff, Paul (Box 3)
    - Walker, Charles A. (Box 1)
    - Wilgus, H.L. (Box 1)
    - Wright, L. Hart (Box 3)
  - Composites and Groups
    - Faculty Members circa 1870 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Members, ca 1880 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Composite 1883 (Box 1)
    - Junior Law Class 1886-1887 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Composite 1887 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States 1886 (Box 4)
    - LLM Class of 1890 (Box 4)
    - LLM Class of 1890 with additional professor (Box 1)
    - Alumni Meeting, Tokyo 1907 (Box 4)
    - Composite of 13 law students/faculty circa 1910 (Box 4)
    - Class photograph 1911 (Box 4)
    - Dedication of Law Quad 1925 (Box 4)
    - Class Photograph 1926 (Box 4)
    - Class Photograph 1930 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Photograph 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - Class Photograph 1938 (Box 1)
    - Snapshots of Professors in Class circa 1940 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Photograph 1959 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Photograph 1981 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Photograph 1992 (Box 4)
    - Clippings from Composites (Box 1)
  - Notable Figures (not affiliated with the University of Michigan)
    - Brandeis, Louis (Box 1)
    - Brennan, William J., Jr. (Box 1)
    - Brown, Henry B. (Box 1)
    - Tom Clark (Box 1)
    - William O. Douglas (Box 1)
    - Abe Fortas (Box 1)
    - Kavanagh, Thomas Matthew (Box 1)
    - Smith, Otis, M. (Box 1)
    - Stewart, Potter (Box 1)
    - Swan, Henry Harrison (Box 1)
    - White, Byron Raymond (Box 1)
  - Unidentified
    - Unidentified individuals (Box 4)
      (two oversized)
- Other Artwork and Documents
  Other Artwork and Documents series is divided into: Law School Grounds, and Printed Materials. Within the subseries Law School Grounds are photographs and drawings of the Law School quadrangle and its surrounding buildings. Within the subseries Printed Materials, is located a small collection of diplomas issued by the University of Michigan Law School as well as a variety of other printed items, including resolutions in praise of a colleague's work, and a guide to the stained glass windows in the Legal Research Library. Much of the materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically.
  - Law School Grounds
    - Sketch of University of Michigan Campus circa 1863 (Box 1)
    - Law School Library circa 1888, 4 photographs (Box 1)
    - Postcards of University of Michigan Campus circa 1904 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of Stained Glass Cartoons in Hutchins Hall (Box 1)
    - Etchings of Law Quad by George New (3) undated (Box 4)
    - Etching of Law Quad 1928 (Box 4)
    - Color Drawing of Law Quad by Carl J. Moline 1974 (Box 4)
    - Photograph of Stained Glass Window in William W. Cook Legal Research Library undated (Box 1)
    - Law Quad Concept Photograph by Balthazar Korab (Box 4)
  - Printed Materials
    - Diplomas
      - Leckie, Frederick L., Certificate of Appointment to Supreme Court of the United States of America (Box 1)
      - Hashimoto, Gisan 1890 (Box 4)
      - Van Zile, Philip T. 1867 (Box 4)
      - Weigle, Maurice 1890 (Box 4)
    - Other Documents
      - Ca. 1899 "Wanted for Murder" Newspaper Clipping, George H. Wright (Box 1)
      - Memorial Resolution, Frederick L. Leckie, 1950 (Box 4)
      - In Honor of Orie Leon Phillips, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Resolution, Alan N. Polasky 1976 (Box 1)
      - International Alumni Reunion Poster 1997 (Box 4)
      - National Order of the Coif, 100 Years, 1902 -- 2002 (Box 4)
      - Explanation of the Law School Flag undated (Box 4)
      - Guide to Stained Glass Windows in William W. Cook Legal Research Library undated (Box 1)
- Photographs (outsize)
  (This provides a box/folder breakdown of the oversized photos. All individual items are listed above.)
  - Alumni
    - Abe-Downey (Box 2)
    - Engel-Murphy (Box 2)
    - Phillips-Williams (Box 2)
  - Faculty
    - Aigler-Durfee (Box 3)
    - Cooley, Thomas McIntyre (Box 3)
    - Estep-Murray (Box 3)
    - Niehuss-Simes (Box 3)
    - Smith-Wright
      - Unidentified (Box 4)
  - Composites and Groups
    - Composites and Groups (Box 4)
- Other Artwork and Documents (outsize)
  - Law School Grounds
    - Law School Grounds (Box 4)
  - Printed Materials
    - Diplomas (Box 4)
    - Other Documents (Box 4)
- Oil Paintings
  The Oil Paintings are not physically part of this collection, but are listed here for convenience. The paintings are large oil portraits done of Law School faculty, alumni, and other notable figures. Most of the portraits are in their original frames, but some of the portraits were removed from their frames for preservation purposes. The framed portraits and the unframed portraits are separately located, with the framed portraits hanging in the Bentley Library connecting bridge in the closed stacks.
  The 1994 "Law School Art Catalog" in the Documentation series contains images of most of the Oil Paintings.
  - Faculty
    (paintings noted as "unframed" are stored in a separate location)
    - Bates, Henry M. circa 1903-1939
      - Portrait (by Ralf Clarkson): seated and facing forward (unframed)
      - Portrait (by John L. Johanson): later in life; seated and looking to his left circa 1940
    - Bogle, Thomas A. circa 1894-1917
    - Brewster, James H. (by Percy Ives) circa 1897-1919 (unframed)
    - Drake, Joseph, (by Leon Makielski) 1921 (unframed)
    - Goddard, Edwin C. circa 1900-1935
      - Portrait: seated in chair (unframed)
      - Portrait (by Leon Makielski): later in life; (unframed)
    - Griffin, Levi T. circa 1886-1897 (unframed)
    - Holbrook, Evans (by Leon Makielski) circa 1907-1932
    - Kirchner, Otto circa 1894-1906
    - Knowlton, Jerome C. (by Percy Ives) 1896
    - Lane, Victor H (by Percy Ives) 1905 (unframed)
    - Smith, Allan F., (by Richard Wilt) 1968
    - Stason, Edwin Blythe circa 1924-1960
      - Portrait (by Alice Reischer): standing in front of bookshelf reading a book
      - Portrait (by Guy Palazzola): seated at desk signing a document
    - Sunderland, Edson Read (by Percy Ives) circa 1904-1944
    - Thompson, Bradley M. circa 1888-1911
    - Walker, Charles Irish circa 1859-1877
    - Wells, William Palmer (by Percy Ives) circa 1874-1891 (unframed)
    - Wilgus, Horace L., (by Percy Ives) circa 1895-1929 (unframed)
  - Non-Faculty
    - Brucker, Wilbur, Secretary of the Army (by Roy C. Gamble) circa 1959
    - Cleveland, Grover (by Percy Ives) (U.S. President) circa 1895
    - Kiiskila, John (by R.W. Suojonen), (alumni) circa 1871-1963
    - Rosenberry, Marvin Bristol (by E.C. Ashford) (alumni; Wisconsin Supreme Court Justice; at age 63) 1931